He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall,
and he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him,
and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits,
Angels, demons and saints in our time
many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism to see and to no reality
as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate
everyday life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen
Damick and Father Stephen De Young, host this live Colin show, focused on enchantment in creation,
The union of the scene and unseen as made by God.
experienced by mankind throughout history. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
So this week, ancient faith is not having live shows.
And as we speak, Father Andrew, I believe, is somewhere
having a burly sweet do that super fast karate chop thing
on his back. So I thought rather than
leaving our our
beloved Lord of Spirit's audience to go lacking this week. I would read another
ancient text that folks may not be familiar with. This time I'm going to be
reading what's called the Babylonian Theodicy and what this actually is is an
the Acadian text from the Neo-Babalonean Empire.
So we're talking about the middle part of...
the First Millennium BC.
And this is essentially a sort of Babylonian version
of the Book of Job.
And here's what I mean by that.
It's a dialogue between a guy who is suffering misfortune
and a friend of his where they go back and forth,
discussing the relationship between
that stuff.
and the gods, the Babylonian gods.
And it's interesting because it is sort of very similar in certain format ways
to the book of Job in the Scriptures.
And so by sort of comparing the two, you get a very different impression
of the Babylonian gods and Yahweh the God of Israel.
if we pay close attention.
So I'm going to read this.
There are gonna be some places where
there's sort of lacune in the text,
where there's chunks missing,
lines missing, words missing.
So there's gonna be places where it gets a little choppy.
I'll try to point those out,
but there's a significant amount of text here
and there's enough that you can make sense
of sort of what's going on.
So, I'll refer...
to because the translation I'm going to be reading refers to them this way as the
sufferer and his friend. So the sufferer says, O sage, come let me speak to you. Let
me recount to you who have suffered greatly. Let me always praise you. Where is one
whose reflective capacity is as great as yours? Who is he whose knowledge could
rival yours? Where is the counselor to whom I can tell of woe? I'm without
recourse, heartache has come upon me.
I was the youngest child when fate claimed my father, my mother who bore me departed to the
land of no return, my father and mother left me, and with no one my guardian."
The friend replies,
"'Consider it friend what you tell as a sorrowful tale, my dear friend, you have let your
mind harbor ill.
You make your estimable discretion feeble-minded, you alter your bright expression to a scowl.
Of course our fathers pay passage to go death's way.
I too will cross the river of the
dead as is commanded from a bold. When you survey teaming humankind altogether, the poor
man sun advanced, someone helped him get rich. Who did favors for the sleek and wealthy?
He who looks to his God has a protector. The humble man who reveres his goddess will garner
wealth. So the friends response is well. If you're suffering this misfortune, he's not saying
here that the
the gods caused it.
He's saying, but this is your way out.
You need to go and find one of the gods
to sort of become your patron.
And when you serve them and offer them sacrifice and worship,
they'll help you out and they'll make your life better.
So then the sufferer responds,
my friend, your mind is a wellspring of depth,
unplummed, the upsurging swell of the ocean
that Brooks and Owen adequacy.
To you then, let me pose a question,
learn what I would say,
for a moment. Here my declaration, my body is shrouded, craving wears me down, my assets have
vanished, my resources dwindled, my energies have turned feeble, my prosperity is at a standstill,
moaning and woe have clouded my features, the grain of my meat is nowhere near satisfying me,
beer the sustenance of humankind as far from being enough. Can a happy life be a certainty?
I wish I knew how that might come about.
So he says, well, it's even worse that I already...
said, I'm not only an orphan, I'm also poor, and I can't even sort of satisfy my own hunger.
He says, I need to know for certain that there's some way I can get to a happy life.
So the friend replies, my well thought out speech is the ultimate in good advice,
but you make your well-ordered insight sound like babble. You force your mind to be scatterbrained
irrational. You render your choices to offerings without conviction.
As to your everlasting unremitting desire, the foremost protection lies in prayer.
The reconciled goddess returns to you.
The reconciled gods will take pity on the fool, the wrongdoer.
I don't think they're worshiping Mr. T. I think that's just a coincidence.
See constantly after the rights of justice,
your mighty one will surely show kindness and will surely grant mercy.
So again, the answer is, well, you just need to go and appease the gods.
Right, you need to go and satisfy.
the gods with your worship and then they'll do good things for you.
Suffer a response,
I bow down before you, my comrade, I apprehend your wisdom, what you say.
Come let me tell you, the onager, the wild-ass that had its fill of wild grass.
Did it carefully carry out a god's intentions?
The savage lion that devoured the choices meet.
Did it bring its offerings to appease a goddess anger?
The parvinu who multiplies his wealth?
Did he weigh out precious gold to the mother guy?
for a family? Have I withheld my offerings? I prayed to my God. I said the blessing over the regular
sacrifice to my goddess in my speech. So he points to two things. First it's kind of an inverse of what
we find often in the Bible. He says, well you look at wild donkeys, you look at lions, you look at
the animals, they all seem to be provided for and they're not making any offerings to any gods.
And then he says, and in fact, that he had been making all
the offerings to the gods, and he still ended up in this mess he's in.
The friend replies,
O date-poll, wealth-giving tree, my precious brother, perfect in all wisdom, a gem of wisdom.
You are a mere child, the purpose of the gods is remote as the netherworld.
Consider that magnificent wild-ass on the plane.
The arrow will gash that headstrong trampler of the leaves.
Look at that lion you called to mind the enemy of livestock.
for the atrocity that Lion committed, the pit yons for him.
The well-heeled Parvinu who treasured up possessions,
a king will put him to the flames before his time.
Would you wish to go the way these have gone?
Seek after the lasting reward of your God.
So basically the friends or spots to those objections
is, well hey, you don't know how things
are gonna ultimately turn out for those wild animals
or for the guy you're talking about who got wealthy.
You know, they, because they're not appeasing the God.
the gods may strike them with misfortune at some point in the future. Whereas you, even
though you're already in misfortune, if you go and make the offerings, then your fate
can change too. You can reverse just like theirs might.
The sufferer replies, your reasoning is a cool breeze, a breath of fresh air for humankind.
Most particular friend, your advice is excellent. Let me put but one matter before you. Those
who seek not after a God.
can go the road of favor. Those who pray to a goddess have grown poor
in destitute. Indeed in my youth I tried to find out the will of my God,
with prayer and supplication I besought my goddess. I bore a yoke of
prophetless servitude. My God decreed for me poverty instead of wealth.
A cripple rises above me, a fool is ahead of me. Rogues are in the ascendant
and I am demoted. So again he's hammering on this. Listen man, I tried that.
I tried to go-
to the Babylonian gods and this is where I ended up, right? That does it work. This quidpro quo idea
of offerings to the gods and then they do for you. It doesn't work, at least with the Babylonian gods.
Right? And so you see here that the Babylonian religious idea of sacrifices, temple offerings as
instrumental to get the gods to do what you want. And he's saying the system is breaking down
because I did that stuff and they're...
not doing what I want.
And the friend is just saying, no, no, keep at it.
Right?
Just keep doing it.
And things will get better.
It'll eventually work.
The friend replies,
adjust knowledgeable one.
Your logic is perverse.
You've cast off justice.
You've scorned divine design.
In your emotional state,
you have an urge to disregard divine ordinances.
The strategy of a God is as remote as the innermost heaven.
the command.
of a goddess cannot be drawn out. Teaming humanity well understands trouble. So he's saying,
look, you know, we can't understand the ways of the gods, right? But you can't just reject
our traditional religion. You can't just reject paying religion. This is the way things have always
been. You have to just keep piously doing these things and eventually things will turn around.
Suffer says I will forsake
I will crave no property. I will ignore my God's regulations. I will trample on his rights.
I will slaughter a calf and I will eat it for food. I will go on the road. I will learn my way around distant places.
I will open a well. I will let loose a flood. I will roam above the far outdoors like a bandit.
I will stave off hunger by forcing entry into one house after another. I will prowl the streets,
casting about ravenous like a beggar. Good fortune lies afar off.
So he's saying
look, I'm telling you it doesn't work, I'm just going to say forget about all this stuff.
I'm just going to go get mine, right?
I'm just going to go get what I need.
I'm going to take it if I have to.
And I'm not worrying about all of this stuff about the Babylonian gods anymore because
doesn't work.
Doesn't work like it's supposed to.
So then there's a section that's kind of broken up here.
and so I'm gonna skip.
it's really choppy. So I'm going to skip this several fragmentary lines and pick up again
where the sufferer says, the son of a king is clad in rags, the son of the destitute
and naked is dressed in fine raiment. The maltster can pay and find his gold while he who
counted red gold shoulders a debt. He who may do with vegetables, sates himself at
a princely banquet with, while the son of the eminent and wealthy has only care of to
the man of sub-
since his fallen, his income is removed.
The friend replies,
You have let your subtle mind wander.
You have overthrown wisdom.
You have spurned propriety.
You have besmirched every code.
Farrah will be the workman's labor
from him who does not work.
He is well served.
He gets what he wants
who follows in the way of a God
and observes his rights.
Be ready for good fortune.
So this is the Babylonian prosperity gospel.
Right.
Just give the gifts to the gods that they want and hey get ready for your whole life to get better
Then there's another gap of the text and we come back with more from the friend as for the rascal who's good will you wanted
The print of his feet will soon disappear the godless swindler who acquires wealth a deadly weapon is in pursuit of him
Unless you serve the will of a god what will be your profit
You who bears the God's yoke will never want...
food though it may be meager. Seek after the favorable breeze of the gods. What you
lost for a year, you will recoup in a moment. Right? So just stick to it. And notice also,
he who bears the gods he will never want for food. Though it may be meager. So you'll have food.
I mean, maybe not much food. He's not promising huge results. The sufferer replies,
I have looked around in society indications of the contrary. God does not block
the progress of a demon, a father hauls a boat up a channel while his first borns for
all's in bed. The eldest son makes his way like a lion, the second son is content to
drive a donkey. The air struts the street like a peddler, the younger son makes provisions
for the destitute. What has it profit in me that I knelt before my God? It is I who
must now bow before my inferior. The rift raft despise me as much as the rich and the
proud. So Suffer keeps coming back to look-a-ban look-a-round.
Look at society. It's not how it works. It's not the people who are really pious toward the Babylonian gods who are the wealthy and the successful and the powerful.
Quite the opposite in many cases. He says this and you notice he's connected here, not only worship of gods, but even hard work.
Hard work doesn't even seem to pay off. The lazy are doing as well or better than the hard working.
working.
The Fred Respond's Adept Scot-
or master of her addition, you blaspheme in the anguish of your thoughts.
Divine purpose is as remote as in her most heaven.
It is too difficult to understand.
People cannot understand it.
Among all creatures the birth god has formed, why should offspring be completely unmatched?
The cow's first calf is inferior.
Her subsequent offspring is twice as big.
The first child is born a weakling.
The second is called a capable warrior.
Even if one tries to apprehend divine intention, people cannot understand it.
the phrase.
response to look around you man, look at how things actually go in society is, well, who
can understand the gods? I mean the Babylon guys, who can understand, who can understand
their ways? Right? But at the same time that he's saying that he's saying, but here's
how it works. Right? And you need to just continue with with this, uh, quid pro quo. Even though
you're not getting your quo.
Suffers.
as pay attention, my friend. Learn my next parry. Consider the well-chosen diction of my
speech. They extoll the words of an important man who was accomplished in murder. They
denigrate the powerless who has committed no crime. They esteem truthful the wicked, to
whom truth is abhorrent. They reject the truthful man who heads the will of God. They fill
the oppressors' strong room with refined gold. They empty the beggars' larder of his
provisions. They shore up the tyrant to
all who's all is crime. They ruin the weak. They oppress the powerless. And as for me,
without means, a part of a new hates me. So he's saying, listen, like, look, like you're
not getting this right? Look at how our society treats the good versus the wicked, right?
only so this is about
honor and shame. This is about who the culture honors. He's like the culture, the other people in our city
don't even honor the good and the pious, but instead the wicked.
The friend responds, and little king of the gods who created teaming humankind,
majestic Aya who pinched off their clay, the queen who fashioned them,
of Mr. Somami gave twisted words to the human race.
They
can doubt them in perpetuity with lies and falsehood.
Solomely they speak well of a rich man.
He's the king they say he has much wealth.
They malign a poor man as a thief.
They lavish mischief upon him.
They conspire to kill him.
They make him suffer every evil because he has no wherewithal.
They bring him to a horrible end.
They snuff him out like an ember.
So the French response is,
well, the reason that the people,
the common people don't esteem good and reject evil
Thank you.
that the gods messed up when they made them. The Babylonian gods who they believed created
them, they say, well, they messed up. And humanity is basically broken. And so the great
mass of humanity out there doesn't really understand what is good at what is evil. So
of course, of course they're going to praise the wicked and and revile the good. Right?
So this red has a very interesting theology that seems to come.
constantly undercut itself.
That seems to be based wholly in tradition, right?
In the traditions of the Babylonian people.
And the one definition of insanity,
which is doing the same thing over and over again
and hoping for different results.
So the sufferer has the concluding word.
You are sympathetic, my friend,
be considerate of my misfortune.
Help me see my distress.
You should be cognizant of it.
Though I am humble, learned, supplicant, I have not seen help or sucker for an instant.
I would pass unobtrusively through the streets of my city.
My voice was not raised, I kept my speaking low, I did not hold my head high, I would
look at the ground.
I was not given a servile praise among my associates.
May the God who has cast me off grant help, may the goddess who has forsaken me take
pity.
Deppard Shammesh will pass your people as a God should.
So it concludes with words of resignation from the person who's suffering, who just says,
look, I'm not being humbled for some wickedness. I've tried to do exactly what you're telling
me to do. This has still been falling me. I don't know what else to do. Hopefully, the Babylonians
God will take pity on me.
As I said, I think if you compare that,
if you compare this kind of confused and
despairing view of the Babylonian gods,
from both participants in this discussion,
to what happens in the book of Job and how the book of Job culminates.
I think there's some richness there in terms of
she really showing the difference between Yahweh,
God of Israel as he revealed himself.
to the people of Israel and the gods of the nations and how they were viewed and interacted
and applied their yoke as the text here says to the people of those nations.